<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-02-05T12:59:15-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Giorgi</title><subtitle>I think, therefore I'm distracted</subtitle><author><name>Giorgi Kvernadze</name></author><entry><title type="html">Introduction to Multilayer Perceptron</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/multilayer-perceptron/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to Multilayer Perceptron" /><published>2019-12-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-12-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/multilayer-perceptron</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/multilayer-perceptron/">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is best suited for people who are familiar with linear classifiers, specifically Logistic Regression&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For the entirety of this post I will be assuming binary classes but everything that I write here can be extended to multi-class problems&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The goal of this post isn’t to be a comprehensive guide about neural networks, rather this is an attempt to show a path from going from logistic regression to a neural network where at each step we intuitively build on something that we already know&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many types of neural networks, each having some advantage over others. In this post I want to introduce the simplest form of a neural network, a Multilayer Perceptron (MLP). MLPs are a powerful method for approximating functions and it’s a relatively simple model to implement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we jump into talking about MLPs, let’s quickly go over linear classifiers. Given training data as pairs &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(\boldsymbol{x}_i, y_i)&lt;/script&gt; where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{x}_i \in \mathbb{R}^n&lt;/script&gt; are our datapoints (observations) and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;y_i \in \{0, 1\}&lt;/script&gt; are their corresponding class labels. The goal is to learn a vector of weights &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{w}&lt;/script&gt; and a bias &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;b&lt;/script&gt; such that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{w}^T\boldsymbol{x} + b \ge 0&lt;/script&gt; if &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{x}&lt;/script&gt; belongs to the positive class and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\boldsymbol{w}^T\boldsymbol{x} + b &lt; 0 %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt; otherwise (belongs to negative class). This decision can be written as the following step function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\text{Prediction} = \begin{cases}
      1 &amp; \boldsymbol{w}^T\boldsymbol{x} + b \ge 0 \\
      0 &amp;  \text{Otherwise}\\
\end{cases} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of Logistic Regression the decision function is characterized by the sigmoid function &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sigma(z) = \frac{1}{1+e^{-z}}&lt;/script&gt; where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;z = \boldsymbol{w}^T\boldsymbol{x} + b&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\text{Prediction} = \begin{cases}
      1 &amp; \sigma(z) \ge \theta \\
      0 &amp;  \text{Otherwise}\\
\end{cases} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\theta&lt;/script&gt; is usually set to be 0.5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: These are actually just a couple of examples of a zoo of functions that people in deep learning literature refer to as activation functions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the dataset is linearly separable this is all fine, since we can always learn &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{w}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;b&lt;/script&gt; that separates the data perfectly. We’re good even if the dataset is almost linearly separable, i.e the data points can be separated with a line, barring a few noisy observations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/blobs.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what can we do if the dataset is highly non-linear? For example something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/circles.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing we could potentially do is to come up with some non-linear transformation function &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\phi(\boldsymbol{x})&lt;/script&gt; such that the data becomes linearly separable. We can then apply that transformation to the original dataset and learn a linear classifier on the transformed dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example in this case we can see that the data points come from two co-centric circles. We can use this information to come up with a function: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\phi(\boldsymbol{x}) = [x_1^2, x_2^2]&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we can learn a vector &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{w}&lt;/script&gt; and bias &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;b&lt;/script&gt; such that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{w}^T\phi(\boldsymbol{x}) + b \ge 0&lt;/script&gt; if &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{x}&lt;/script&gt; is positive and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\boldsymbol{w}^T\phi(\boldsymbol{x}) + b &lt; 0 %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt; otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/circles_transformed_clf.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This works, but what can we do when it’s not obvious what the underlying function is? What if we’re working in high dimensions where we can’t visualize the shape of the dataset? In general it’s hard to come up with these transformation functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s another idea, instead of learning one linear classifier let’s try to learn three linear classifiers and then combine them to get something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/circles3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know how to learn a single linear classifier but how can we learn three linear classifiers that can produce a result like this? The naive approach would be to try to learn them independently using different random initializations and hope that they converge to something like what we want. But this approach is doomed from the beginning since each classifier will try to fit the whole data while ignoring what the other classifiers are doing. In other words there will be no cooperation since none of the classifiers will be ‘aware’ of each other. This is the opposite of what we want. We want/need the classifiers to work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where MLPs come in. A two-layer MLP can actually do both of the aforementioned things. It can learn a non-linear transformation that makes the dataset linearly separable and it can learn multiple linear classifiers that cooperate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- **Neural Networks:**

By far the most common way of introducing neural networks is with the notion of computational graphs. While I do think that computational graphs are an important concept to understand, I do not think that they are the best way to be introduced to neural networks. Instead I will be using concepts that hopefully you the reader are familiar with. These are the essential operations for neural networks: matrix multiplication, non-linear activation functions and function composition. --&gt;

&lt;!-- In general it's better to teach new ideas using concepts and terms that a person is already familiar with, since this allows for the already known things to function as a foundation to be built on, rather than trying build from scratch.

The term 'neural networks' itself is kind of misleading. It creates an image of a brain like structure and it feeds into the whole hype about AI taking over. Neural networks in reality are nothing but a chain of matrix multiplications followed by non-linear functions.   --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Layer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A layer in the context of an MLP is nothing but a linear transformation followed by an activation function. We will use our idea of learning multiple classifiers but instead of looking at them independently, we’ll define them together as a single layer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s define three classifiers &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(\boldsymbol{w_1}, b_1), (\boldsymbol{w_2}, b_3)&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(\boldsymbol{w_3}, b_3)&lt;/script&gt;. For compactness, let’s combine all of the weights into a single matrix and all of the biases into a vector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\boldsymbol{W} = \begin{bmatrix}
           \boldsymbol{w_1} \\
           \boldsymbol{w_2} \\
           \boldsymbol{w_3} \\
         \end{bmatrix} = \begin{bmatrix}
                    w_1^{(1)} &amp; w_1^{(2)}\\
                    w_2^{(1)} &amp; w_2^{(2)}\\
                    w_3^{(1)} &amp; w_3^{(2)}\\
                  \end{bmatrix} \boldsymbol{b} = \begin{bmatrix}
                             b_1 \\
                             b_2 \\
                             b_3 \\
                           \end{bmatrix} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we need to get the classification decision from all three classifiers. We might be tempted to use the step function but for technical reasons, that will become clear later on, we require the function to be differentiable and since the step function is not, we cannot use it. We could however use the sigmoid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classification decision from each of the classifiers can then be obtained by applying &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sigma&lt;/script&gt; element-wise to each of the three outputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\sigma(\boldsymbol{Wx} + \boldsymbol{b}) = \begin{bmatrix}
\sigma(\boldsymbol{w_1x} + b_1) \\
\sigma(\boldsymbol{w_2x} + b_2) \\
\sigma(\boldsymbol{w_3x} + b_3) \\
\end{bmatrix}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that what we have is a linear transformation &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{s} = \boldsymbol{Wx} + \boldsymbol{b}&lt;/script&gt;, followed by a non-linear activation &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{h} = \sigma(\boldsymbol{s})&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the neural network lingo what we defined above is a hidden layer with 3 sigmoid units. Note that we need not use sigmoid here. As I mentioned in the beginning of this post, the sigmoid function is just one example of many activation functions. We could use anything we want (as long as it’s differentiable). Here are a few alternatives: Tanh, ReLu, LeakyReLu etc. The most popular choice in practice is the ReLu activation defined as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\text{ReLu}(z)=\max(0, z)&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Second Layer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first layer gives us outputs from the classifiers but we still need a way to combine them into one final classification decision. For example if the outputs from the layer are &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;[0.7, 0.5, 0.1]&lt;/script&gt; what should the classification decision be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s define another classifier &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(\boldsymbol{w}_{final}, b_{final})&lt;/script&gt; that will take the outputs of the three classifiers as input and will produce a final output: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{w}_{final}^T\sigma(\boldsymbol{Wx} + \boldsymbol{b}) + b_{final}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally in order to get the final classification decision, we apply a sigmoid activation to the result of this as well. Combining all the parts we get that our function is defined as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\text{MLP}(\boldsymbol{x}) =\sigma(\boldsymbol{w}_{final}^T\sigma(\boldsymbol{Wx} + \boldsymbol{b}) + b_{final})&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one line actually fully defines our two-layer MLP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why do we need activations?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I defined the first layer, I said that we needed to get a classification decision from each of the classifiers. This isn’t quite right. We don’t need a classification decision. What we actually need is a response. A response that is non-linear in the input. Non-linear activation functions are actually what makes this whole thing work. If for example in our hidden layer we removed the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sigma&lt;/script&gt; activation and replaced it with an identity, the MLP will actually become a linear classifier which would mean that we will not be able represent the non-linear shape of the input data. To convince yourself, write out the MLP without any activations and see that it reduces to a linear function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- **More layers**

In practice we usually have many such layers each connected to each other, i.e the output of one becomes the input for to next one. Chaining layers like this is actually the same as function composition. If we define each layer as a function, $$f_i(x) = g(\boldsymbol{W}_i\boldsymbol{x}+b_i)$$, where $$g$$ is some non-linear activation then an n-layer MLP can be written as the function composition $$MLP(x) = f_n(f_{n-1}(...(f_1(x))) $$. The depth of a network corresponds to $$n$$, when $$n &gt; 2$$, people refer to this network as deep (this is where the term deep learning comes from). The width of a network corresponds to the number of units in each of the layer.

The functions $$f_1,f_2, ..., f_{n-1}$$ are all learning a transformations with the ultimate goal to make the input $$X$$ linearly separable for the final layer $$f_n$$. This is the essence of deep learning. Every neural network one way or another is trying to learn a transformation function on the input space that can render the data linearly separable. --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You are free to skip ahead this section if you don’t care about knowing all the nitty gritty details of learning the parameters of the MLP.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have managed to define a two-layer MLP but we still need a way to learn the parameters of the function. The entire function is fully differentiable and this is no accident. As I said earlier, we refrained from using the step-function as an activation because of technical reasons. Well the technical reason is that differentiability is nice and we like it because it allows us to use well known optimization algorithms like Gradient Descent (GD).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we define the loss function, the goal will be to minimize the loss w.r.t to the parameters &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{W}, \boldsymbol{b}, \boldsymbol{w}_{final}, b_{final}&lt;/script&gt;. This will require application of the chain rule and if we’re not careful about giving names to intermediate values, it will quickly get hairy. So let’s do that first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{s}_1 = \boldsymbol{Wx} + \boldsymbol{b}&lt;/script&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{h} = \sigma(\boldsymbol{s}_1)&lt;/script&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s_2 = \boldsymbol{w}^T_{final}\boldsymbol{h} + b_{final}&lt;/script&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\hat{y} = \sigma(s_2)&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay now that we have our intermediate values named, let’s define the loss function. We’re going to be using binary cross-entropy (negative log likelihood) which is defined as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;L(y, \hat{y}) = \frac{1}{n} \sum_{i=1}^n -y_i\log\hat{y_i} - (1-y_i)\log(1-\hat{y_i})&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we start the tedious process of taking partial derivatives of a composed function I want to remind you that the goal is to compute these four partial derivatives: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial L}{\partial \boldsymbol{w}_{final}}, \frac{\partial L}{\partial b_{final}}, \frac{\partial L}{\partial \boldsymbol{W}}, \frac{\partial L}{\partial \boldsymbol{b}}&lt;/script&gt;. If we have these values, we can use them to update the parameters at each step of GD. Using the chain rule we can write down each of the partial derivatives as a product:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial L}{\partial \boldsymbol{w}_{final}} = \frac{\partial L}{\partial \hat{y}}\frac{\partial \hat{y}}{\partial s_2}\frac{\partial s_2}{\partial \boldsymbol{w}_{final}}&lt;/script&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial L}{\partial b_{final}} = \frac{\partial L}{\partial \hat{y}}\frac{\partial \hat{y}}{\partial s_2}\frac{\partial s_2}{\partial b_{final}}&lt;/script&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial L}{\partial \boldsymbol{W}} = \frac{\partial L}{\partial \hat{y}}\frac{\partial \hat{y}}{\partial s_2}\frac{\partial s_2}{\partial \boldsymbol{h}}\frac{\partial \boldsymbol{h}}{\partial \boldsymbol{s}_1}\frac{\partial \boldsymbol{s}_1}{\partial \boldsymbol{W}}&lt;/script&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial L}{\partial \boldsymbol{b}} = \frac{\partial L}{\partial \hat{y}}\frac{\partial \hat{y}}{\partial s_2}\frac{\partial s_2}{\partial \boldsymbol{h}}\frac{\partial \boldsymbol{h}}{\partial \boldsymbol{s}_1}\frac{\partial \boldsymbol{s}_1}{\partial \boldsymbol{b}}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know this looks complex but it really isn’t that complicated. All we’re doing is taking a partial derivative of the loss with respect to each of the learnable parameters. Since the loss is a composition function we have to use chain rule. That’s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial L}{\partial \hat{y}}\frac{\partial \hat{y}}{\partial s_2}&lt;/script&gt; is shared among all of them and that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L, \hat{y}, s_2&lt;/script&gt; are all scalar variables therefore the derivatives are relatively easy to compute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial L}{\partial \hat{y}} = \frac{\hat{y}-y}{\hat{y}(1-\hat{y})}&lt;/script&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial \hat{y}}{\partial s_2} = \hat{y}(1-\hat{y})&lt;/script&gt; (Recall that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sigma^{'}(z) = (1-\sigma(z))\sigma(z)&lt;/script&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial L}{\partial \hat{y}}\frac{\partial \hat{y}}{\partial s_2} = \hat{y}-y&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing down the chain we get:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial s_2}{\partial \boldsymbol{w}_{final}} = \boldsymbol{h}&lt;/script&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial s_2}{\partial b_{final}} = 1&lt;/script&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial s_2}{\partial \boldsymbol{h}} = \boldsymbol{w}_{final}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now since, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{h}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{s_1}&lt;/script&gt; are both vectors, the partial &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial \boldsymbol{h}}{\partial \boldsymbol{s_1}}&lt;/script&gt; will be a matrix, however it will be a diagonal matrix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial \boldsymbol{h}}{\partial \boldsymbol{s_1}} = \text{diag}((\boldsymbol{1} - \boldsymbol{h}) \odot \boldsymbol{h})&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which can be replaced by an element-wise multiplication in the chain as: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\odot (\boldsymbol{1} - \boldsymbol{h}) \odot \boldsymbol{h}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The partial derivative &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial \boldsymbol{s_1}}{\partial \boldsymbol{W}}&lt;/script&gt; is the most complicated to compute. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{s_1}&lt;/script&gt; is a vector and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{W}&lt;/script&gt; is a matrix, therefore the result of the partial derivative will be a 3 dimensional tensor! But fortunately, we will be able to reduce it to something more simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of computing the partial derivative with respect to entire weight matrix, let’s instead take derivatives with respect to each of the classifiers &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{w_1}, \boldsymbol{w_2},&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{w_3}&lt;/script&gt; (These would correspond to the rows of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{W}&lt;/script&gt;). Each of these derivatives will be a matrix instead of a tensor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\frac{\partial \boldsymbol{s_1}}{\partial \boldsymbol{w_1}} = \begin{bmatrix}
             x_1 &amp;&amp; x_2\\
             0 &amp;&amp; 0 \\
             0 &amp;&amp; 0 \\
           \end{bmatrix} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\frac{\partial \boldsymbol{s_1}}{\partial \boldsymbol{w_2}} = \begin{bmatrix}
            0 &amp;&amp; 0\\
            x_1 &amp;&amp; x_2 \\
            0 &amp;&amp; 0 \\
          \end{bmatrix} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\frac{\partial \boldsymbol{s_1}}{\partial \boldsymbol{w_3}} = \begin{bmatrix}
            0 &amp;&amp; 0\\
            0 &amp;&amp; 0 \\
            x_1 &amp;&amp; x_2 \\
          \end{bmatrix} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that we’re gonna be using these values in a multiplication. We can use this fact to simplify the expression for the derivative. Let &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial L}{\partial \hat{y}}\frac{\partial \hat{y}}{\partial s_2}\frac{\partial s_2}{\partial \boldsymbol{h}}\frac{\partial \boldsymbol{h}}{\partial \boldsymbol{s}_1} = \boldsymbol{\delta}&lt;/script&gt;, then we’ll have&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{\delta} \frac{\partial \boldsymbol{s_1}}{\partial \boldsymbol{w_1}} = [\delta_1x_1, \delta_1x_2]&lt;/script&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{\delta} \frac{\partial \boldsymbol{s_1}}{\partial \boldsymbol{w_2}} = [\delta_2x_1, \delta_2x_2]&lt;/script&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{\delta} \frac{\partial \boldsymbol{s_1}}{\partial \boldsymbol{w_3}} = [\delta_3x_1, \delta_3x_2]&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which implies that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\boldsymbol{\delta}\frac{\partial \boldsymbol{s_1}}{\partial \boldsymbol{W}} = \begin{bmatrix}
          \delta_1x_1 &amp;&amp; \delta_1x_2\\
          \delta_2x_1 &amp;&amp; \delta_2x_2 \\
          \delta_3x_1 &amp;&amp; \delta_3x_2 \\
        \end{bmatrix} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can rewrite this compactly as an &lt;em&gt;outer product&lt;/em&gt; between &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{\delta}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{x}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial L}{\partial \hat{y}}\frac{\partial \hat{y}}{\partial s_2}\frac{\partial s_2}{\partial \boldsymbol{h}}\frac{\partial \boldsymbol{h}}{\partial \boldsymbol{s}_1}\frac{\partial \boldsymbol{s_1}}{\partial \boldsymbol{W}} = \boldsymbol{\delta} \otimes \boldsymbol{x}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial \boldsymbol{s_1}}{\partial \boldsymbol{b}} = \text{diag}(\boldsymbol{1}) = \boldsymbol{I}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting everything together:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial L}{\partial \boldsymbol{w}_{final}} = (\hat{y} - y)\boldsymbol{h}&lt;/script&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial L}{\partial b_{final}} = \hat{y} - y&lt;/script&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial L}{\partial \boldsymbol{W}} = ((\hat{y} - y)\boldsymbol{w}_{final}\odot (\boldsymbol{1} - \boldsymbol{h}) \odot \boldsymbol{h}) \otimes \boldsymbol{x}&lt;/script&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial L}{\partial \boldsymbol{b}} = ((\hat{y} - y)\boldsymbol{w}_{final}\odot (\boldsymbol{1} - \boldsymbol{h}) \odot \boldsymbol{h})^T&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have noticed that all of this is for a single datapoint &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{x}&lt;/script&gt;, we wouldn’t do this in practice. It is much more preferable to have everything computed for a batch of inputs &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boldsymbol{X}&lt;/script&gt;, this allows us to update the parameters much more efficiently. I highly recommend you redo all of the computations of the partial derivatives in matrix form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also purposefully skipped over a lot of the details. I wanted this block of the post to serve as a reference for your own solutions rather than a complete guide. Here are some useful notes that can come in handy if you want to do everything from scratch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cs231n.stanford.edu/vecDerivs.pdf&quot;&gt;Vector, Matrix, and Tensor Derivatives - Erik Learned-Miller&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.stanford.edu/class/cs224n/readings/gradient-notes.pdf&quot;&gt;Computing Neural Network Gradients - Kevin Clark&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Result&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to how we started, we said that if we had a transformation function that could make the dataset linearly separable then learning would be easy. Well &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\phi(\boldsymbol{x}) = \sigma(\boldsymbol{Wx} + \boldsymbol{b})&lt;/script&gt; will actually be that transformation that makes the dataset linearly separable. This is what the data looks like after applying that learned function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/projection.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And these are the three linear classifiers that are learned in the hidden layer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/hidden_classifiers.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;pretty neat huh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a link to the Jupyter notebook that contains all the code for this post: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/colonialjelly/multilayer-perceptron/blob/master/multilayer-perceptron.ipynb&quot;&gt;Code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Giorgi Kvernadze</name></author><summary type="html">There are many types of neural networks, each having some advantage over others, in this post I want to introduce the simplest form of a neural network, a Multi-Layer Perceptron (MLP). MLPs are a powerful method for approximating functions and it's a relatively simple model to implement.</summary></entry></feed>